it's January 13 2009 teen Happy New Year
to you all and thank you for joining the
Q&A so I'll start with a couple of
announcements
first I suppose is that I'm leaving
patreon January 15th some of you may
know that that's I suppose in protest
over their treatment of Carl Benjamin
perhaps better known as sargon of akkad
patreon like many companies seems to
believe that their role now is to act as
censor for speech patterns or speech
content that they regard as unacceptable
and I think that they made a big mistake
with Sargon and so both Dave Rubin and I
and also sam Harris have decided to
leave patreon and that's going to be
official as of January 15th so those of
you who are my patron on subscribers if
you're interested in continuing with
that subscription you can go to my
website at Jordan V Peterson comm and
there's a support button there in the
menu and you can use that system I'm
also trying to design a system that at
least in principle might work as a
reasonable replacement for patreon
that's a couple of months away but we're
working hard on a ton we're getting
legal advice we're going to set up
multiple payment channels so that it
won't be easy for people to be kicked
off by credit card companies or let's
call them virtue signaling ethical types
who think that their role is to police
free speech so I think this is a very
bad precedent that patroness and the
credit card companies - I can't imagine
it's difficult to imagine a more
dystopian scenario than to have the
large tech companies in combination with
the credit card companies monitor your
spending to decide when what you're
doing is sufficiently ethical by their
by the standards of the
people who are running their let's call
them safety and security speech
monitoring programs it's just such a
terrible idea so mm-hmm
there's that that I'm also working on my
new book quite a lot but actually it's
tentatively titled beyond order twelve
more rules for life or perhaps beyond
mere order I haven't decided on that yet
I can tell you what the rules are maybe
you'd be interested in that
so I'll give you a list of them the
first one is do not carelessly denigrate
social institutions or creative
achievement rule to imagine who you
could be and then aim single-mindedly at
that rule 3 work as hard as you can work
as hard as you possibly can on at least
one thing and see what happens
rule 4 do not hide unwanted things in
the fog rule 5 abandoned ideology
abandoned ideology rule 6 notice that
opportunity lurks where responsibility
has been abdicated rule 7 do not do
things that you hate rule 8 try to make
one room in your house as beautiful as
possible rule 9 if old memories still
make you cry write them down carefully
and completely rule 10 plan and work
diligently to maintain the romance in
your relationship rule 11 be grateful in
spite of your suffering and then rule 12
do not allow yourself to become
resentful deceitful or arrogant in
principle that book will be published in
January 2020 so and I'm supposed to have
the manuscript in sometime within the
next six months and I have a first draft
done and I'm working hard on the repeat
edits it's going to be published
simultaneously in the UK and the US and
Canada I'm working with three different
editors and so that's that part of the
announcement so I'm hoping I'm really
hoping that I can make the next book
better they're gonna be a pair it'll be
a paired coffee with the first one I'm
probably going to publish it with a
black cover to go with the white cover
of 12 rules and I'm hoping that I can
make it into a better book and that the
two together will make a very complete
set so that's the plan we'll see how it
goes
the last announcement I guess no two
more announcements I'm going to
Switzerland tomorrow my daughter is
having surgery there to get her ankle
fixed again we're hoping that that will
go well I'm also doing a talk in Zurich
then I have three talks in California
information for them is at Jordan B
Peterson comm forward-slash events and
then in February my wife and I are going
my wife Tammy and I are going to
Australia New Zealand and I believe we
have 15 talks scheduled there over the
course of about a month and then I think
in March and April I'm going to
concentrate mostly on writing and then
perhaps we're going to go to Europe and
so that's for a month or two that will
depend to some degree on the writing
schedule but that's the plan at the
moment I have some good podcasts coming
up I talked to General Stanley
McChrystal last week about his new book
on leadership and the myths that
surround it and some of the initiatives
that he's been working on in the United
States and so McChrystal was the
commander of the American forces in
Afghanistan and so it was very
interesting to talk to him and well
there's a variety of other things going
on too but I won't tell you any more
about those for the time being I think
what I'll do instead is turn to some
questions so I guess maybe I could also
give a bit of a recap for 2018 so Tammy
and I have gone to about
fifteen cities now something like that
her google trip trackers showed that she
had gone six times around the world mine
said twenty and so that's obviously
wrong because I traveled mostly with her
but there was a lot of traveling last
year and I spoke to about two hundred
and fifty thousand people and that was a
very all of that was very positive
experience that lectures have been
really well heartwarming to use an old
term I mean it's really something to see
that many people gather together and and
listen and happen and participate in a
discussion about about psychological and
and philosophical and spiritual issues
that's as deep as I can manage anyways
and it seems to be quite gripping for
the audience and good for everyone and
so they're very very positive
experiences which is partly why we've
been able to sustain this speaking pace
so that's been good oh we also have a
discount by the way we my partners and I
decided to encourage everybody to make
their New Year's resolutions in a
sophisticated and comprehensive way and
so we have this program some of you have
heard about this at self authoring calm
called future authoring and the future
authoring program helps you write out a
vision for the future to think through
what you'd like your life to be like if
you were taking care of yourself
properly to consider your friends and
your family and your career and your
education and your use of time outside
of work and your ability to resist
temptation the kind of temptation that
might drag you down and and how you
might take care of yourself mentally and
physically and to write about that and
then to write a counter story which was
where you might be three to five years
down the road if you let all your bad
habits get out of control and then to
write a strategic plan it's a very
useful program we've used it with
lots of university students in
particular although it's for adults of
all ages and if you're a university
student and you complete the program it
seems to increase the probability that
you'll stay in university by about
twenty-five percent something like that
it seems particularly useful by the way
for men for reasons that we don't
exactly understand maybe because they're
underperforming women academically and
it also improves people's grades but
there's a large literature in the
industrial organizational area also
indicating that if you're like if you're
working and you make a personal plan of
this sort then your overall productivity
increases by about ten percent which is
a lot and you're you're more likely to
be physically and mentally healthy and
so I would really recommend trying this
even you can try the program you don't
have to do a perfect job at it it
doesn't really matter because you're
trying to set out a bit of a vision and
a plan for your life and you need that
because you need direction and you need
purpose and you need the constraints of
a vision to help you be less anxious and
uncertain and and you you have that
anxiety and uncertainty reduction does
occur if you have a decent map of where
it is that you're headed the coupon code
is my 2019 New Year's 2019 NY 2019 and
if you go to the self authoring site and
click on the products menu item and go
to future authoring you can just enter
in that coupon code and it's 50% off so
I think the total price is seven dollars
and forty-five cents which is actually
pretty damn cheap if what it does is
help structure your future and I really
do think this is a helpful program we've
worked on it a lot and tested a lot and
it's based on solid behavioral
psychological principles allied with I
would say a certain degree of optimistic
philosophy and it's well it's a good
thing to do and this is a good time to
do it so if you're interested all that
information will be in the description
of the video as well so that's basically
that
as far as I can tell I don't think I
have anything else to tell you Oh 12
rules for life has sold about 3 million
copies now so I guess I'm telling you
that it's become very popular in Korea
where it's sold about 200,000 copies
which is quite interesting and something
I wouldn't have necessarily expected so
all right so let's answer some questions
and see how that goes can you talk about
your own specific experiences / methods
used with integrating the shadow yeah
well I can actually I think a tremendous
amount of what you might regard as
shadow integration which in the parlance
of behavioral psychologists would be
something like assertiveness training
all right it's training and how to stand
up for yourself and and for your let's
say for your better self which would be
the self that you could use productively
over a medium to long period of time
that would be of use to you but also of
use to people around you so it's a self
that's founded by the necessity of
taking care of yourself but also
simultaneously taking care of the people
around you I think that the simplest way
to start that work is to consult your
resentment you know it's easy to become
bitter about life and to become angry
because of course life is difficult and
it's full of disappointments and people
are also subject to be trail on the part
of themselves and on the part of people
that hypothetically care for them and so
it's easy to get bitter and to be
resentful and resentment is a very
useful emotion even though I think it's
one of the most damaging emotions if
it's not dealt with properly so if
you're resentful basically means only
one of two things it either means you
should grow up and quit whining and get
on with your life or it means that
you're being subject to tyrannical
forces of one form or another maybe
emanating
you may be a consequence of the natural
environment may be a consequence of
society your being subject to tyrannical
forces and you're not putting your own
best interests forward like in that
broader sense that I described I don't
mean your selfish narrow interests that
only serve the purposes of instantaneous
gratification I mean your own best
interests in terms of developing your
character over the span of your life if
you're resentful it either means that
you're immature and that you should grow
the hell up and so you need to figure
out how much of your resentment is is is
that and maybe allied with the desire to
find other things or people to blame but
the other possible option is that you
have something to say or do right
because you're in a situation where
you're violating your own internal
ethical standards and you're being
required pressured let's say to say
things you don't believe or to do things
that you believe to be wrong and you
need to determine you need to start to
strategize and plan how you can rectify
that so that you can say what you mean
like if you're negotiating with a
marital partner for example and there
are issues in your marriage that aren't
making you happy well the first thing is
you have to take note of that right to
see that you're actually unhappy the
second is that you have to be willing to
engage in a certain amount of conflict
because in order to sort out what's
disturbing you you're going to have to
lay your concerns out on the table and
say well look this is bothering me you
don't have to say well I'm right and
you're wrong and you have to fix this
you have to say well I've noticed that
this pattern of interaction or lack of
interaction say in our relationship is
making me resentful and angry and the
danger of that of course is you're going
to take it out on yourself and your
partner
the danger is passion passive
aggressiveness you know you're not going
to respond to your partner positively
when they do something good if you're
resentful about them and you're not
going to respond to yourself properly
and so you have to lay it out on the
table but sort of in a spirit of
ignorant humility it's like look I'm
frustrated I'm feeling this way about
our relationship
here's what I think might be going wrong
maybe on my part and maybe on your part
and here's what I envision as a possible
solution that's also really necessary if
you're going to say what you have to say
which is to manifest yourself properly
in the world is you can't just complain
about what's wrong you have to think
well what would my minimal preconditions
for satisfaction be you have to offer
that to the person that you're
negotiating with and so then you learn
to abide by the truth to the degree that
you can do that and no one does it
perfectly you know but it's very useful
because you're not storing up a whole
sequence of memories about how you were
unfairly treated and abused and betray
instead you're trying to stay on top of
it and to note your unhappiness and
dissatisfaction when it manifests itself
and to accept that that's the case and
then to analyze that to see if it's your
problem like I said with regards to
maturity or if it indicates that there's
an injustice in the manner in which you
and the world are interacting and then
to work to set that right even in small
ways and so it's it's a matter of
character logical development and that
makes you that makes you stronger over
time and partly what you need you know
in order to do that is you have to
really understand and we do this this is
why we built in the future authoring
program we built this section where you
have to outline your most dismal future
right what your future would be like if
you let all your bad habits and
characterological weaknesses have the
upper hand and the reason we did this is
because you can't be you can't
straighten yourself out merely as a
consequence of hope let's say you lay on
a vision for the future and you think
about what your life would be what you'd
like your life to be like and then that
makes you hopeful and it motivates you
because it gives you something
worthwhile and higher order to work for
right and that's useful that's positive
emotion working for you because positive
emotion is experienced in relationship
to goals but it's not as if not as
useful as also being chased by something
you're terrified by and if you have a
good sense of how you can fall apart if
you stay
week and just exactly what kind of hell
that would be then when you determine to
do something like to tell the truth and
to say what you think and to not do
things that you hate then you're going
to be pulled along by the purpose that
your vision has provided for you but
also pushed along by your desire to
avoid the worst forms of Hell that
you've already outlined for yourself
personally and that can also help you be
brave enough to stand up in the
situation that we would require a
conflict because if you have something
to say and you have something to
negotiate about with someone then
there's going to be a certain amount of
conflictual dialogue that accompanies
that right to lay out a set of problems
and to describe the fact forthrightly
that those problems characterize a
relationship and then to seek for
solutions is quite stressful in the
short term and it's really easy to avoid
and so people avoid it all the time and
then they store up grievances across the
span of the relationships and eventually
the grievances mount to the point where
they return in monstrous form and just
eat everything up that's where you get
divorces or that's where you explode it
your boss and end up fired or that's
where you you know you develop high
blood pressure over 15 years because you
can't stand all the accumulated months
all the accumulated monsters in your
closet and and you drink yourself into
oblivion because he can't stand your
life that's all you know very
counterproductive but it's easy to avoid
that necessary conflict on a
moment-to-moment basis because it's very
stressful to speak forthrightly about
genuine conflicts especially when you're
dealing with important parts of your
life but otherwise you don't straighten
them out and then you have to carry all
that forward so you need to be terrified
of the consequences of not speaking your
piece and that can counterbalance the
terror of actually trying to have a
conversation so well you know and you
also have to look with regards to the
the shadow ideas like you have to get in
touch with the depths of your anger you
know lots of people are resentful about
all sorts of things they're resentful
about Oh
women and they're resentful about men
and they're resentful about the
patriarchy and they're resentful about
the left wing and they're resentful
about the right wing and they're
resentful about politicians and they're
resentful about the cataclysmic force of
nature and its ability to make people
sickened and suffer and they're
resentful about their own inadequacies
in the boat they're bad parenting and
God like the list is just bloody endless
and that can make you very very angry
and that's part of that resentment and
cynical and bitter and dark and full of
fantasies about destruction and the
desire to bring things down and the wish
that everyone else suffered and the
desire to shake your fist at God and all
of that's really dark you know Young
said well the shadow of the human shadow
extends all the way down to hell and he
really meant that you know because all
the terrible things that people are
motivated to do are associated with that
shadow domain and like none of you are
any none of you are Saints in any
likelihood you have a terrible capacity
for destructiveness and when you start
to consult your resentment and to see
how angry you are
it can terrify you to see the depths of
that anger sometimes that will manifest
itself in very destructive fantasies you
know which you might not want to become
conscious of because they're so brutal
let's say and so aggressive that you
can't even believe that you generate
them the nice person that's you it's
like so it's quite frightening to open
that door and see all that and that also
associates you with the entire dark
shadow of mankind right the the Satanic
element of the human character and but
it opens the door to understanding as
well - to understanding how people can
do terrible things because you could see
yourself as one of the people who could
do terrible things that's really useful
you know because then you well then
maybe you start to be motivated to be
the sort of person who wouldn't do
terrible things you know if you can
really come to terms with the fact that
that's part and parcel of you it also is
some in perverse sense it's also a
discovery of your own strength though
because you know if you have that desire
for aggression that does
for destruction than that that that
ability to fantasize in that aggressive
manner it also means that you can
incorporate some of that into your
speech and into your actions so that
you're a lot more movable right and and
a lot more of a force to contend with it
can give you some respect for yourself
when you realize that you're a force of
destruction as well as creation and then
you're also more likely to treat
yourself with a bit more intelligent
caution you know to know that you're but
part of you is a ticking bomb in some
sense that can go off and so you you you
tried a bit more lightly around yourself
and and maybe you encourage people to
tread a bit more lightly around you as
well which isn't such a bad thing and
all the people that I really admired
that I know have a clearly dangerous
side and you don't want to get you don't
want to have that activated any more
than necessary but it's also what makes
them respectable and strong especially
if they have that under control so well
that's a bit of a dialogue about shadow
integration it's a very challenging
undertaking you know to pull in that
dark side of your character and and that
would be all the things that you've
repressed or failed to develop as a
consequence of trying to be a harmless
and well let's say a harmless and
harmless citizen who looks virtuous on
the surface that's the union persona and
you need that because everybody needs a
mask that they wear in public like a
suit you know so that we can tolerate
seeing each other on the street we don't
have to look right into our depths every
time we interact we need that persona
but that has to be transcendent and the
way to transcend that is to integrate
the darker parts of the character
they're very useful that aggression
that's sexual demand for example all of
that's very difficult to socialize that
competitiveness but unbelievably useful
in terms of force of character if you
could manage it
richard asks how can i help my parents
to sort themselves out that's question
one how can i talk about the resentments
of my childhood a way that benefits them
instead of giving them guilt yeah well
those are two very difficult questions
how can you help your parents to sort
themselves out well I guess the first
question would be or do they want to
sort themselves so because it's not that
easy to help people if they don't want
to be helped if they do want to be
helped like listening is really a good
strategy
you know people you've got the question
right because you said how can I help my
parents to sort themselves out which is
very different than how can I sort my
parents out you help people to sort
themselves out once they have decided to
do so by giving them the opportunity to
talk about their concerns and also to
outline what potential solutions might
be and you don't want to offer too many
pieces of advice while you're doing that
because it turns out that people are
much more likely to implement a strategy
of improvement if they generate it
themselves and then also you don't steal
the accomplishment from them like let's
say you came to me with a bunch of
problems and I said well here's what you
can do about that and then you went out
and did it and it worked and and then in
some sense that's not your
accomplishment I mean it is insofar as
you implement it but it's not insofar as
it was something that I planned and your
intimation of that your intubation of
the fact that the delight in success and
the responsibility for six success might
have been stolen from you by
well-meaning advice is going to
interfere with the probability that
you'll implement the solution and so
it's best to let people talk through
their own problems like well what's the
problem that's what you ask what's the
problem what do you think it's not right
about your life and then people will
throw up with a bunch of things that
they're complaining about or resentful
about and
and it might be quite an extensive list
and they'll feel guilty about it because
they don't want to burden you with it
and but they need to get it all off
their chest right they need to get the
cards on the table so also some things
know when you're talking to your wife or
your husband or your intimate partner or
a child for that matter so when you have
a close relationship with this if
they've got some things to complain
about which they undoubtedly do they're
going to complain about a lot more
things than they're actually upset about
because they'll have gathered up
irritations
that have been unspoken and aggravations
and fears and they'll all be upsetting
them emotionally and they don't know
exactly what they are until they
articulate them you know we say well
what are you upset about well I don't
know well how can you not know well the
answer is there's all sorts of things
that you respond to emotionally before
you can articulate them then you get
upset and you explode and you yell and
you lay out all the things you might be
angry about and you're impulsive and you
overstate your case and you accuse
people of things that you don't even
believe all of that's part of the
process of laying your cards out on the
table you have complex situations that
are disturbing you and you don't know
what they are exactly you have to kind
of guess so you say well it might be
this it might be that it might be this
it might be you and this is why it's
your fault and you get accusatory and
then if you're listening to all that you
have to just be patient and let the
person get all their cards out on the
table even if some of that involves
accusations about you which you don't
have to immediately you don't have to
immediately jump to the conclusion that
those accusations are accurate or that
you have to defend yourself you know and
I'm not believe me I'm not saying this
is easy because it's not but you listen
to the person lay out there their deck
of complaints and the first thing you'll
find is that they will take 50 percent
or maybe more 75 percent of the cards
off the table right away because once
they've articulated out those concerns
they'll find that they're not really
central they're not really the issue and
so that leaves a smaller number of
genuine problems and then you can ask
people again well here's the problem can
you think of any way if you could
conceptualize how
would be better in relationship to that
problem well what would a solution look
like even in principle and then they
might say well I don't know and then
they have to guess and lay their cards
out on the table about what a solution
might look like if they say they don't
know that often means they don't want to
think about it and a little bit of
encouragement isn't in order and maybe a
little bit of pressure but you want
people to formulate a vision of what the
situation would look like if the problem
was solved and then they might find it
very daunting because the solution looks
so difficult that they don't see any
pathway to it and so then the next part
of the discussion is well are there some
things that you could do that would be
small steps that you would be interested
in doing that you think you would do
that would move you to the solution and
maybe those things could be implemented
tentatively and behavioral psychologists
call that collaborative empiricism so
you'll come and see a behavioral
psychologist and lay out your problems
and then the two of you will negotiate
towards the beginnings of a solution
what could you do this week that might
make that problem slightly better and so
you talk through what's practical and
what's implementable you have to be
honest about that because you don't want
to set yourself up with a plan that's so
complicated you won't implement it then
you say to the person if you're the
psychologist you say well look we've got
a couple of ideas about what you can do
this week that might make this situation
slightly better why do you go and
implement them and then come back next
week and we'll talk about whether or not
that worked and work would be you did
implement it and that it did have the
desired solution and if it didn't work
meaning you didn't implement it or the
solution didn't emerge then there's
there's the opportunity for
renegotiation so you can think about it
strategically the first issue is well if
something needs to be sorted out the
first question is what the hell is the
problem and the answer that is you
probably don't know the problem is I'm
upset and disturbed and angry and
resentful and bitter and unhappy and
anxious and in pain and lonesome I'm
suffering from an excess of negative
emotion and perhaps from a certain
amount of hopelessness so the problem is
the emotional
circumstance and that might be
associated with some real problems right
some real practical problems so you lay
all that out and say okay well what is
the problem landscape look like right so
that's the strategic move and then as I
said that will generally simplify the
problem landscape then you do think the
same thing with a set of potential
solutions well what would the solutions
look like cuz you're not gonna be able
to solve a problem unless you at least
know what a solution might look like
that would actually what would you say
that would that you would find
acceptable and then the next Pro issue
is to lay out the strategies for the
attainment of that solution and you know
sometimes it might be some of these
solutions might be dismal like you know
if you've got someone who's ill in your
family
the solution might be well well we need
a cure you know that's the only solution
that will suffice but you don't know how
to pursue the cure or maybe one doesn't
exist so then you have to think of well
a lower order and less satisfying
solution which would be well maybe we
can cope we're gonna learn to cope with
this so that it's the least amount of
Hell possible and and maybe that maybe
that even that's too much you might have
to say well we're gonna try to make this
next week when we're coping with this
better than the last week you know and
and maybe you can't even do that it has
to just be the next day you look for
whatever small steps forward you can
take that will make things less wretched
and horrible than they currently are you
know to put it rather bluntly
and that requires the willingness to
face the problem the humility to know
that you don't have the solution at hand
the willingness to listen to how the
other people that you're talking to
formulate the problems and formulate the
solutions it's crucially important right
to have them do that work themselves
it's it's also you could think about it
this way too is that if you listen to
someone come up with a solution
you don't undergo the neurological
transformations necessary to change your
character but if you come up with the
solutions yourself you know if you
articulate the problem
you articulate the solutions then you've
changed your own character in a way that
increases the probability that you're
going to act out what you do and that
requires real patience to to let people
stumble through to their own problem
solutions because someone might lay out
a set of problems and you think oh my
god I know what you could do about that
but it doesn't really matter if you know
you know and I'm also not saying that
sometimes advice is helpful you know
sometimes you can give someone a hint
but man you have to be careful with that
because there's a real element of theft
that's associated okay with it now
Richard also asked how can I talk about
the resentments of my childhood in a way
that benefits them instead of giving
them guilt I don't know if I can answer
that question Richard because it's it's
not a question that's see what I would
ask if you came to talk to me and you
had that question I would say first of
all well what resentments list them out
man write him down okay so that you know
what they are because all those each of
those resentments is going to be a
different thing and the strategy that's
associated with each might vary as a
consequence of the particularity of the
resentment so I would say you should
start by writing them down like what's
your problem exactly here's all the
things that I can think of that I'm
angry about with regard to my childhood
write that down and then see which ones
are still living and then you have to
figure out well what do you want from
your parents exactly do you do you want
them to apologize do you want them to
understand what they did wrong do you
want to punish them do you want to get
let them get you let them learn to know
you better do you want to change the way
they're interacting with you now do you
want to learn your own lessons from your
bad experience so that when you're a
parent you don't make the same mistake
you merely want to have a chance to
express yourself like it's very
difficult to to answer your question
because I don't know what your goal is
right so but and
and I don't need to know you need to
know what are the resentments so we can
walk through the process where to
describe
lay them out and comprehensively you
might want to make a list of everything
that you think you might conceivably be
annoyed about with regards to your
parents no matter how trivial right
because that way you you scour your
memory four four four four four things
that you're holding onto in a bitter way
and maybe you have your justification
I'm not suggesting that you don't but
you need to discover what baggage you're
carrying then you have to figure out
well what can I let go of and what score
and I would say what's really core is if
there are ways that your parents treated
you that are still affecting you or that
are affecting your relationships with
them now those really need to be dealt
with because they're not done they're
not in the past right they're not even
resentments of your childhood they're
still part of your ongoing life and so
okay so now you have all your
resentments laid out I guess I would say
you know something like look mom and dad
there's something I need to talk to you
about that's been bothering me for a
long time and I'd pick one of the more
trivial things to begin with like here's
a memory I have and don't get all high
and mighty about it because you know you
might have misconstrued the situation as
a child it's highly probable and they
may have had their reasons and you may
not even remember the situation let's
say correctly or the way they remember
to say well here's here's something that
happened when I was a kid in it it still
bothers man do you remember what
happened that's an open-ended question
do you remember what happened why did
this why did this go this way and then I
would do an awful lot of listening you
know because you are trying to gather
information and the more your parents
can tell you about what happened in
those situations I would say the better
off you're likely to be so that's about
all I can say about that that's fairly
delineated approach to general
discussions about difficult things right
but I would say don't be afraid of don't
be more afraid of engaging in this
process than you are afraid of not
engaging in it like every relationship
you have
gonna have problems in it and you know
you don't want to jump to a intense
psychological discussion with every
little bump but if if there's something
of medium to long term permanence that's
disturbing you or a pattern that repeats
itself at least three times let's say
well then that might be something that's
worthy of discussion or your discovery
that you're you know very dissatisfied
with the way the relationship is going
and you have to have the conflict
necessary to sort that out and it's
going to be conflict with you and the
car and the person that you're talking
to but the aim should be the
establishment of something like fully
informed fully negotiated medium to long
term peace that's what you're aiming at
if you have any sense
Oh Cody said it took me seven months but
I completed all the self authoring suit
in July I'm still not motivated to do
anything and waste all of my time what
do I do well well the first question is
is it true that you're not motivated to
do anything and is it true that you
waste all of your time it seems highly
unlikely to me that both of those things
are a hundred percent true so one of the
things you might notice is are there
anything is there anything that you're
motivated to do presume you're motivated
to eat although perhaps not and I'm not
being smart about this um partly what I
would say is two things you might need
some smaller goals like you have to
shrink your goals to the point where
you've established a plan forward that
consists of steps that not only you
would be willing to take but that you
would take and so some of that humility
it's like man I'm stuck I can barely do
anything it's okay like well I'm I'm
laying in bed for seven hours a day
well could I lay in bed for six hours
and six and a half hours tomorrow you
know or while I'm in bed could I do
something somewhat useful could I read a
book and I read one page of a book can I
read a paragraph of a book you have to
find that those steps forward that you
would take I really think it's useful to
make friends with something like a
Google Calendar you know or whatever
calendar program you might want to use
and start designing days that you would
like to have because that's the right
way to use a calendar and everyone out
there that's listening you should you
should use a calendar to structure your
days because if you know what you're
doing tomorrow it decreases your
anxieties substantially because you need
that kind of structure you need a
pathway you need to know you need to
have a map and you need to know where
you're located on the map and you need
to know how you're moving forward and
that gives you hope because you're
moving towards goals that you regard as
worthwhile and it stops you from being
anxious because you're not entirely
directionless and lost and so learning
how to manage your time is useful
you can start with a calendar you can
start with simple things like you can
put in well when you're likely to go to
bed and when you're likely to get up and
regulating that's useful that should be
relatively ritualistically consistent
it's very difficult to get your life in
order if your sleep-wake schedule is
completely random or if it's not aligned
with like day and night and if it's not
aligned with the normative practices of
other people and so you may have to
learn to get your sleep wake cycle
regulated properly and then the same
with your eating schedule those are very
basic things and you can do that badly
but that's what you want to approximate
three meals a day let's say because
that's what people do normatively and
and then you have to add small goals now
if that doesn't work like if you can't
make the goals small enough to achieve
you know it might be that you're not
being humble enough with regards to your
conceptions of your own ability but you
can tell if the goal that you put
forward is a reasonable one if you're
actually implementing it because if
you're not then by definition it's not a
reasonable goal you know like let's say
you're you're sleeping all the time in
your room is just a bloody complete
disaster you know and you think well I
should clean up my room it's like well
maybe you can't but maybe tomorrow you
could hang up two shirts you know or you
could we could move two shirts from your
bedroom to the laundry room or you could
bag up a bag of dirty clothes but you
could conceivably take to a laundromat
and you just do that one thing you know
if you do if your room's a catastrophe
and you do that one thing and then you
did one thing like that for 15 days or
20 days maybe your place would be in
order and so the trick is to get the
trajectory right and Kody if you if that
doesn't work then you're gonna need to
talk to somebody you know maybe you need
a partner that that that you can discuss
these things with where you both have a
commitment like a mutual commitment to
attaining a certain set of goals
you know that could be a friend it could
be somebody that you find online it
could be and it could be a professional
but if you find that you
self cannot you just can't get this
going then you're gonna have to reach
out to someone else to give you a hand
maybe you need to sit down with a parent
or a friend or somebody that you love
and go over the self authoring suite
with them to go over the future
authoring plans and to discuss how that
might be implemented you know because if
you can't do it on your own then and
maybe you shouldn't have to then you
have to reach out to other people and so
make your goals smaller see if you can
make friends with a schedule or a
calendar this is really important all of
you out there who aren't doing this like
I would say all of the people that I
know who have become successful in any
way use a structured means to organize
their time they have lists of things to
do like they have everyday there's a
list of things to do that day every week
there's a list of things to do that week
every month there's a list of things to
do that month you know at every level of
temporal resolution there's a sequence
of plans and those plans are implemented
on a day to day basis you cannot be and
successful isn't the right way of
thinking about it because I'm not
thinking about you know I'm not really
thinking about rising up the corporate
ladder you know you know what I mean and
that's sort of what success has come to
mean in our culture that isn't what I
mean you can't have a life that you're
going to find acceptable without that
because you need the vision and the
plans to give you purpose and direction
that's where all your positive emotion
comes from all your motivation is laying
out plans that are worth attaining and
then observing yourself moving towards
them that's the source of most positive
meaning and then also without that
structure you're so lost that you're
going to be anxious and overwhelmed it's
really like being in a foreign country
like isolated and alone with no map I
don't know where the hell I am I don't
know what the hell I'm doing you know
the rains are going to come and the
storms are going to come and maybe it's
winter
and I don't know where I am or where I'm
going and then the last thing Cody is
like rely on some other people man
you know maybe you'll be able to return
the favor in the future I know you'll
feel bad maybe that you have to go to
someone else you feel weak and you know
that you're taking advantage of them but
people like to be helpful they really do
and and so it's a mark of trust in
someone and confidence in them that you
would ask to have a serious conversation
with them and so and if you don't have
someone like that then you need to find
somebody like that and maybe that means
you have to interact more in online
communities or maybe you have to get the
hell out there in the world there's lots
of meetup groups and that sort of thing
online that have organized themselves
and you can go there and hide in the
back for a while and not talk to anybody
but you're gonna get it I get the hell
out there and and you know make some
social connections because you cannot
live alone we're social creatures and
you need help and maybe you'll be able
to offer some help at some point in the
future too so well okay Rose says I'm
consumed by envy I can hardly stand to
read or watch or listen to anyone more
successful than myself in what
directions have my aiming wrong okay
well look Rose it's pretty damn useful
to figure out that you're consumed by
envy that's a good start you know that
that's a real self-realization and an
important one okay so the first thing we
might ask is well it's it's likely
reasonable for you to observe that
that's not optimal for you right because
envy that's that resentment that I was
talking about earlier or even worse than
jealousy it's like it it's not a
pleasant phenomenological state it's not
a pleasant state of experience okay so
look let's look at it this way well what
are you envious of you know you say I
can hardly stand to read or watch or
listen to anyone more successful than
myself well that's pretty vague Rose and
you want to tighten up your envy a bit
it's like you'll find that there are
certain people that you're predicting
the envious of another issues
accomplishments really don't disturb you
let's say so the first thing you want to
do is figure out which people it is that
you're particularly envious of and then
you want to figure out well what is it
that you think they have now you know
they probably have a lot more problems
than you think and so part of the
pathology of envy is that you look at
someone who's successful and you assume
that that success defines them across
all the important dimensions of their
life and that's rarely the case
and so you know there's a naive optimism
and envy and that's reflected in the
fact that you think that the person
you're jealous of has everything that a
person would need and that's rarely the
case but that's somewhat besides the
point look in your Envy lurks the
beginnings of a structure of ambition
you wouldn't be envious of something if
you didn't believe that that was a value
that you should possess okay so the
first thing is make a list of all the
people you're envious of and then figure
out what it is about them that you envy
okay now those are your goals all of a
sudden right now you might be doubtful
that you can attain those goals and I
don't know what the goals would be you
know like maybe it's beauty for God's
sake maybe you're envious maybe just for
the sake of argument you assume that
you're not a very good-looking person we
can assume you're not blessed by the
same set of physical attributes that a
Hollywood starlet might manifest you
know and maybe you're envious of that
it's like why you might start to think
well in first of all you might think
about whether or not there are
dimensions of evaluation along which
someone might be judged that are as
important or more important than
physical attractiveness right because
there's multi there's multiple
dimensions along which a person's
positive attributes might be rank
ordered and considered so you might want
to broaden out your conceptualization of
what constitutes the good in human
action but then like if it is a matter
of attractiveness then you may have to
and I'm picking this one because it's a
particularly difficult one
attractiveness it's like well what could
you do
how often do you get your haircut that
is it flattering you have someone
professional doing it do you know how to
use makeup properly and carefully you
know are you in reasonable physical
condition or are there other steps that
you could take to put yourself in
reasonable physical condition do you
have some nice clothes like it's a
matter of decomposition so let's assume
we'll be optimistic about this you're
envious okay well that means there's
some things you value you don't have
them but it's the beginnings of a
philosophical stance so you lay out what
it is you're envious about and you think
well these persons these people have
this and this and this and this and I
don't and that's unfair and it might be
unfair it's probably not an unfairness
that specifically aimed at you it's
probably more a general reflection of
the unfairness and the inequality that's
part of life and that's worth knowing
but in any case you lay out your envy
and you and you delve deep into it and
you find out well here's what I want
because you're in these envious because
you see other people that have what you
want okay good now all of a sudden you
know what you want well that's useful
terrifying because you might see that
it's so distant from you but you can at
least lay out and then maybe even admit
to yourself what you want because the
other thing is is that you'd be unlikely
to be so envious if you weren't hiding
from yourself what it is that you that
you truly want you might be terrified to
admit it because well once you admit it
then you know what you want and you know
when you're failing you know and and by
hiding what you want from yourself well
then you can hide to some degree the
fact that you're not getting it and that
you're failing and and it's no wonder
that people do that so make a list of
what you're envious of extract from that
the virtues that you would like to
pursue understand clearly that unless
you pursue those virtues you're not
going to get what you want and the envy
will consume you more and that's like a
good pathway to hell that's not a good
thing and so make a plan here's some
things that other people have that I
want how can I start to move
words having some of that myself and
that's a that's the right way to deal
with it so because the other what's the
alternative you're gonna tear these
people down or or or or manifest hatred
for for them and maybe take your revenge
when you can on the people around you
because you're so angry and you're gonna
tear yourself into pieces like you said
consumed by envy right and that's like
that's a predator metaphor Envy is
something that's eating you up god
that's not good you know but it's really
good that you've at least admitted it
that start part of that confrontation
with the shadow so you can see your dark
side there you know and you can look at
your fantasies because if you're
consumed by envy no doubt you have some
pretty damn brutal fantasies I wish this
is what would happen to that person know
God they think they're so smart it's
like I hope they fall and I get a chance
to kick them while I'm down well they're
down maybe you could join a Twitter mob
and take them out if they make a mistake
you know but that can also get you in
touch with the dark side of you that
maybe has the ability to to put forward
some commitment to moving forward in the
future that can make you tough and
strong and so you might also start with
the consideration that you could move in
the direction that you desire right if
you are willing to make the proper
sacrifices I'm willing to do the work
and maybe if you can find out what would
truly motivate you which might be the
desire to cease being consumed by Envy
that would be a good start and then to
pursue these goals that are implicit in
your jealousy well then you have a
direction for your life so in what
directions are you aiming wrong well
you're assuming that you're being
unfairly treated and that it's and that
there's something personal about that
now you probably are being unfairly
treated in some sense because that's
just the human condition I would say
like there's a real arbitrary element of
life you're subject to the depredations
of nature and the tyranny of culture and
your own appalling shortcomings you know
and that's life it's not personal
exactly and that's worth knowing it's
part of the standard human condition
you should aim at rectifying your envy
and some of that's going to be dropping
that bitter resentment and the other is
going to be pursuing what you need to
pursue to allow you to view your life as
at least acceptable right so so there's
hope in the enve once you admit it
because it gives you a moral direction
hello dr. Peterson what would you advise
to a person who has the courage to defy
the crowd but doesn't have the verbal
skills to debate real-time well look
there's lots of ways of defining the
crowd let's say I mean you could live
your life the way that you want live it
that's a matter of action you know and
they say actions speak louder than words
and one of the best things you could
possibly be is a inspirational example
so that's not nothing
that's that something live properly in
your defiance of the crowd right make
your own course allow yourself to be
guided by your own genuine principles
you don't necessarily have to advertise
that which is in some sense what you're
doing when you when you're debating
because you're taking the manner in
which you act like if you're an
integrated person and you're
articulating that but maybe you can't do
that because you don't have the verbal
skills well then the question would be
maybe you should develop some more
verbal skills like I don't know this for
sure Dave you know but but generally
it's useful how do you do that
doesn't hurt to read really doesn't hurt
to write you know a little bit of
writing every day clarifies your
thinking it's a hard thing to do and
it's an unlikely thing most people won't
do it but man you know you wouldn't be
asking me this question if you didn't
think at some level that some
improvement in your verbal ability would
be useful to you well so how do you do
that you read you
think you're right the reason you write
is because writing forces you to
articulate your thoughts it organizes
your brain around whatever it is that
you're writing about it
one of the easiest ways to write there
isn't any real easy way but the easiest
ways to write is to write down a problem
it's like what's what what problem is
bothering me we can write about that
first of all to get the problem clear
because that's a hard thing then you
start to write about what my possible
solutions be and if you fight with those
solutions because you know you want to
kill off the stupid ones and then you
know maybe you need to learn to speak
more fluently maybe you need to what
what might we say you could try a class
in improvisation and maybe that's too
daunting you could join a speaker's club
like Toastmasters you could try talking
more at dinner parties a little bit more
once you formulate your thoughts you
have to be willing to be somewhat of a
bumbling fool to begin with right
because you're gonna not if and maybe
you're better your verbal skills are
better than you think they are you know
and you're just self-conscious but you
have to practice putting yourself
forward a little bit and tentatively you
can do a lot of that you know a lot of
that initial learning how to interact
with people though by asking them
questions about what they think and then
responding instead of being too
concerned about putting your old point
forward so all right so what's the
answer
what would I advise to the person who
has the courage to defy the crowd good
live according to your principles right
and that's not a verbal thing and you
can be a good example and that's a major
accomplishment but then if you need to
improve your verbal ability which is
generally a good thing then those are
the ways to do it read write speak and
and and understand that developing those
abilities might be of tremendous use to
you you know because it's one thing to
live properly and that's not a trivial
thing but it
another thing to be able to articulate
yourself and to be able to negotiate and
generally speaking there's nothing about
that that isn't advantageous and even
introverted and anxious people can learn
to do that you know it's those are
learnable skills it's not easy but but
but you can manage it you can also you
can also speak carefully you know and
listen to what you're saying and only
try to say things that you think are
true that's also unbelievably useful you
have to feel that out like is this
really what I believe or am i putting it
forward well because I want to look good
or I want to dominate or or I want to
express obliquely an emotion that I'm
too cowardly to come out and confront
directly or am I being manipulative
there's lots of reasons that people use
language but what you really should use
it for is to state what you believe to
be true and then to let the consequences
of that unfold and so that can also help
you simple truths bluntly stated can be
very powerful you don't need a lot of
verbal fluency under those circumstances
if there's evidence of strength of
character behind it so the daodejing
speaks of acting naturally well I don't
know if that's true if it's acting
naturally it depends on what you mean by
naturally the daodejing speaks of acting
in a manner that balances yin and yang
that balances chaos in order and that
means that you're speaking in the right
place at the right time about the right
things and that's allied with part of
what I just discussed with regards to
speaking the truth how is one to put
their foot down and change / better
their condition without in unnaturally
manipulating their world
well the fundamental answer to that is
to speak the truth and to let the car
secuence --is of that unfold but then
the trick is well how is it that you
come to speak the truth well in order to
do that as far as I can tell you have to
be terrified of the consequences of not
speaking the truth and and part of that
is well look do you want the truth on
your side or not do you want to do you
want to be facing the truth as an enemy
or do you want to have the truth behind
you as an ally and the truth is reality
and I I don't see that you want reality
as an enemy and so if what you do is use
your language to represent reality as
accurately as you possibly can
now given all your inadequacies and
biases you're bound to make errors but
that's the goal then you have the force
of reality behind you it's it's as if
you've you know where you are you might
not like it and you maybe you know maybe
it's a terrible craggy chasm full of
lava and water but at least you can see
where the obstacles are and you can pick
your way through it so and then the
naturalness is well from the Taoist
perspective in some sense yours you're
you're aiming at being at peace with the
world and that means accepting it in
some sense for what it is and you can't
speak the truth unless you're willing to
do that and that means that to a large
degree it means what means exploring the
depths of yin and yang of order and
chaos the order to know that like there
are tyrannical forces of foot and some
of them are operating you and some of
them operate in the social world and and
some of them operate for that matter in
the natural world
too much crushing order and on the
chaotic side there's the possibility of
nihilism and hopelessness and depression
and that a complete Cataclysm and so
you're you're there's cliffs on both
sides of you
you have to be aware of that because you
don't want to fall into those cliffs and
there's a thin pathway between them that
you can that you can walk down if you're
careful and you feel your way down that
pathway by noting how what you say
noting whether what you say puts a
foundation underneath you that's there's
a New Testament injunction to that goal
to build your house on a rock and not on
sand and and what's the rock well the
rock is the truth and integrity of your
character and of your voice that's what
it is
and you you see you want to aim at
something Noble that's the alliance with
God that's one way of thinking about it
you want to serve the highest good and
you have to think very hard about what
that is I mean we know what it is to
some degree or we have some we have some
collective conception of that you know
it would be peace that would be
something it would be the willingness
and desire to treat other people like
you would like to be treated if you were
treating yourself properly it's that as
well it's it's characterological
nobility it's the desire to serve the
good it's truth and beauty and all of
those classic virtues all integrated
into a single thing you want to serve
that and then you and then having aimed
at that you won't do and that that that
that governs how you're going to see the
world right that's senseless and since
the that sets the lens or sets the frame
through which the world manifests itself
to you right so it's as if you're
getting your spectacles adjusted
properly and then the world reveals
itself to you and then you use your
language to articulate that and that's
that's the that's naturally there is no
it's not natural it's very difficult now
you know if you don't do that
what you do is end up you you you end up
using your language to manipulate people
into giving you what you want and that's
not helpful because you know what do you
know about what you want give me give me
one second give me one second sorry
about that my son I'm in my son's
basement my house is being renovated in
Toronto for well til this afternoon and
he's got a new puppy and he was rolling
a bone upstairs
on the floor for this puppy it's very
cute by the way this puppy yeah that's
making quite a lot of racket so I just
had to take care of that so just give
him a good cuffing no I just asked him
just told him that the ball was rolling
around so look part of this is faith in
truth you know like really it's it's
hard to it's hard to emphasize this
importantly enough you have to make a
decision in your life at some point look
about how you're going to use your words
like you can use them instrumentally and
you can use them to manipulate people
you say well this is what I want from
this situation and here's how I'm going
to have to craft my words to get it or
you can think well I'm oriented properly
in the world and I'm going to say what I
think and let things happen and those
are two different they're really two
different modes of being I wrote about
this in 12 rules for life they're really
two different modes of being and the lad
the latter one which is faith in truth
that's the same as faith in the logos by
the way from a symbolic perspective it's
the faith that truth is that which turns
uninhabitable chaos into habitable order
it's the truth that
as that and so you you tell the truth
and you throw caution to the wind and it
doesn't mean you tell the truth stupidly
because telling the truth stupidly isn't
truthful you have to do it very
carefully and very strategically
strategically well the strategic part
the goal is to get better all the time
at carefully articulating what
constitutes the truth you know it seems
obvious to me in some sense it's like
you got to really think this through
it's like what do you want on your side
you want falsehood on your side it's
like who thinks that you really think
that you're gonna be able to lie and
manipulate your your way through the
world and that you're gonna get away
with that like there's an arrogance that
goes along with that arrogance in belief
that arrogance of belief in your
capability to deceive and that you're
gonna pull the wool over everyone's eyes
right you're gonna deceive yourself
because you're gonna believe in your own
maliciousness and mendacious nassif
other people cuz they're stupid and they
won't catch on and you're gonna see
you're gonna deceive God and reality
itself because it's not going to snap
back and take you out if you bend and
distort it like that's so foolish you
don't have a hope none of that you might
get away with your your lies for a
certain amount of time but they're gonna
aggregate and take you out man at every
level not least your own guilt and your
own self contempt and so so where was
that
well that's good answer to that question
I agree we don't live in a tyrannical
patriarchy can you provide a better
explanation for the iniquities women
face especially lateness of the right to
vote etc well you know a hundred and
thirty years ago let's say let's take
1895 just as our starting point in the
world wasn't the same place as it is now
you know rights and privileges spread as
the social and economic conditions make
their manifestation possible to some
degree to some degree and I'm not
suggesting that men haven't oppressed
women and that women haven't oppressed
men Christ we've been at each other's
throats in many ways throughout the
entire course of human history men at
the throats of men men at the throats of
women women at the throats of men women
at the throats of women parents at the
throats of children like there's no
shortage of contentiousness and tyranny
that characterizes human history so but
in 1895 the average person in the
Western world lived on less than a
dollar a day they bited in today's money
way below the current UN standards from
her poverty life was very very hard
there is no reliable birth control like
you can't underestimate the radical
consequences of reliable birth control
know that that that opened up the world
to women and it's not just birth control
it's a whole variety of technological
transformations and and also an increase
in the safety of the street a hundred
contributing factors that have opened up
the world to the freedom of women but a
huge part of that was the collective
striving of men and women to free
themselves from the absolute tyranny of
hand to both exist
you know what woman was well let's say
sexually mature back at that time around
15 or 16 very likely to be married soon
after that partly because sex outside of
marriage was so unbelievably dangerous
very high probability of pregnancy and
then of death in childbirth and then it
and then death of children and then
continual pregnancy women weren't the
same even biologically speaking that the
birth control pill is a biological
revolution and it took a long time to
extend the full coterie of rights to
people even men it was like Jesus most
men in Eastern Europe for example were
serfs until the late 1800s
fundamentally slaves it's it's it's not
as if the common person has had the
right to vote for any substantial amount
of time in some countries for a couple
of hundred years and that's all like
we're we're clambering out of the great
darkness of biological history and
creating a culture where people have
enough freedom to be to exercise what
would optimally be their full set of
rights and to say that that didn't
happen at the patent in the past
primarily because of the patriarchal
dominion of men is I think an escape
from full confrontation with the
absolute dreadful horror of biological
history it's an it's a wish that all of
the things about life that are deeply
troublesome and terrible are a
consequence of the errors made by those
who control the social structure and God
it would be really something if they had
that much power you know it's like well
we can make things bad or good by women
by Fiat it's like no you're you're
facing the terrible dragon of nature and
she's something awful to behold and your
your your your tyrannical patriarchy is
a relatively ineffective force in the
face of the absolute depredations of
mother nature I mean even now we're
powerful technologically compared
to how we have been in the past and you
know we've extended our life a lot but
we still only manage about 80 years and
a lot of that is still characterized by
my mental and physical illness you know
we're still subject to the limitations
the awful limitations of biology ways
that are almost too terrifying to behold
and so we we shy away from that and say
well it's all all the suffering as a
consequence of something that's
oppressive and under the control of
human beings it's like I know I wish
that was the case but it isn't and
that's not to say that social structures
lack corruption but it's not as if a
hundred and fifty years ago all men were
free and all women were enslaved the
truth of the matter is a hundred and
fifty years ago virtually everyone was
enslaved so and it's it's a long bloody
hole out of that you know what a
tremendous amount of that has taken
place over the last 130 years with the
absolutely revolution and living
standard and an availability of food and
proliferation of consumer items and the
construction of the formulation of
labor-saving devices you know that freed
women from the the grinding misery of
constant domestic work for tens of hours
a week at extraordinarily low pay and
the and the the provision of universally
accessible hygienic facilities toilets
everywhere is a big deal allows people
to move around and to operate out in the
world and and tampons and sanitary
products and birth control and all of
that
Jesus women were oppressed because
people were oppressed and perhaps women
were more oppressed than men although
even that's not obvious because you know
men suffered brutally in warfare
absolutely brutally and and and died at
a rate if you eliminate childbirth
deaths from the equation
in a rate that exceeded the rate that
women died at and were required to
sacrifice themselves for the protection
of women and children it's like human
history's a nightmare and that nightmare
involves incredible difficulty in
struggling forward to survive and we
emerged out of that men and women
together and have been attempting to
free each other to the degree that
that's possible in the course of that
struggle and so that's how it looks to
me you have talked about earning your
knowledge how do you define you guys you
put up some viciously good questions
today man I gotta say these are tough
questions they're very good questions so
this is Devon M you've talked about
earning your knowledge how do you define
this and earn it
when is it ok to debate ideas like yours
if they are not your own well I would
say it's okay to debate them right away
if what you're trying to do is to test
them and learn more about them right but
it's not okay if you're trying to put
them forward as if they're your own and
to obtain something approximating
unearned moral superiority by doing so
so that means to have the ideas and to
discuss them but not to identify with
them as if they are defining characters
that defining features of your own
personality how do you earn knowledge
well and all your elementary school
teachers when you're writing an essay
said you got to put it in your own words
think well what does that mean you can't
just copy a sentence it has to be in
your own words and you know to me that
was never very well explained to me but
there was something to it it's like for
knowledge to be yours you have to
integrate it with your own experience
you have to see how that applies to your
own case and then have
story to tell about how that's the case
that's personal right so it's the
intermingling of the abstract with the
personal that makes it real
it's the intermingling of the epic with
the particular or the archetypal with
the with the concrete that makes
something real and so of an idea is
still an abstraction if you're just
parroting it it also means that you
haven't learned to use it as a tool you
haven't started to apply it in your own
life because you could say well here's
an idea that I came across and here's
how I implemented it and here's what I
learned when I implemented it and then
that's definitely yours right because
you're you can kind of tell because
you're recounting your knowledge in a
manner that no one else could do and and
that's what gives it that ring of
genuineness right that's what it means
in some sense to speak from the heart
it's like well here's my experience with
this idea and you can say - well here's
how I understand this idea and you
reformulate that in your own terms and
that means that you associate it with
your own but the only with the unique
particularity --zz of your own
experience and then I would also say it
means that you've acted out the ideas
and tested them like in in the world and
that you have your own stories to tell
about that and that's how you make it
your own it's like you go to the tool
store the hardware store and you buy a
hammer you know and then you start to
use the hammer to hammer in nails and
you learn how to use the hammer you
learn how to use the saw and then you
know at some point that saw sort of
becomes yours you know how to use it and
it's the same with these ideas is like
you don't just you you don't just say
the words you're not just a puppet
mouthing the words they've become part
and parcel of your own philosophy the
way that you perceive the world the way
that you construe things in the way that
you act and the world you've tested them
and you have your own you have something
to add to them that's yours personally
you know and if you if you're having a
discussion with someone and
they're talking about things that don't
have those characteristics right that
they haven't made personal then the
conversation is almost never interesting
it's because the person is it's just an
they're just they really are an empty
shell through which ideologue ideology
because shayzon's slogans are pouring
there's nothing about that that's
compelling because you don't see the
grappling you don't see that the other
person has grappled with the ideas and
come to their own unique conclusions and
it really is in that mingling of the
abstract and the particular that
compelling wisdom is to be found and so
that's that's and then concretely
speaking well there's ways of earning
your knowledge and part of that is
reformulating it in your own words
that's thinking it through right and
discussing it until you have it at hand
you can talk about it and you can
generalize from it because you truly
understand it but a huge part of that is
also putting it into practice than
deriving your own conclusions as a
consequence and some of that can be done
with debate it's like here's an idea I
came across and here's the idea and
here's what I think it means and this is
how I think it would change things if I
put it into practice this is how I
understand this idea and what do you
think of that like that's a good debate
or discussion you know because then the
other person can say well I don't really
agree with the way you've formulated
that or I don't agree with your
conclusions and hopefully it's a real
discussion and not just one upmanship
you know because that's a pretty dull
game and then well then you get clearer
about what it is that the idea is and
how it is that you would use it as a
tool in your own life and that's the
right way to think about ideas to you
know is well partly they're they're
tools for looking at the world with
because you have to look at the world
with tools because you can't look at the
whole world so you're looking at the
world through a tool like structure and
then the ideas themselves are too alike
and they need to be used and and worn a
bit in your hands before they're before
they're yours
so how
you ever thought about engaging in a
public debate with slavish jiseok he has
many interesting observations on the
topic of ideology and that would be a
good conversation conversation yes we
have a tentative we have been speaking
tentatively about the possibility of
having a public discussion in Toronto in
April and so we're negotiating and we'll
see how that goes
we'll see if he's available and if I'm
available if we can agree on a set of
topics if we can if we can undertake all
the complex detailed negotiations
necessary to make something like that
successful in the public sphere I'm
confident enough that this will occur
that I've already downloaded about six
of his books because I really want to
start understanding what he has to say
and think before undertaking that so so
yes I have thought about it more than
thought about it the offer is out the
negotiations are underway how do you
maintain a stable identity when you are
plagued by bouts of depression and
anxiety well the first thing we might
say is that you can't you know what I
mean if you're plagued by boats of
depression and anxiety that does
destabilize your identity so it's almost
by definition but having said that look
this is when habit and plan and strategy
are so useful so in the periods of
depression that I've had what sustained
some of them were long and and and
certainly the most unpleasant
experiences of my life
you this is when you need a philosophy
let's say that's aligned with your
vision and your strategy to sustain you
because what would what would happen to
me is that I know I have these a vision
and I suppose the vision is of a world
that's better in in that's
less likely to descend into ideological
catastrophe and where people are more
responsible and more awake and more
educated and and healthier all of that a
vision of a better world you know a
world is less hellish at least but also
a better world and some sense of what
role I might play in that and then so
that's very motivating like it's a
profound gold to try to make things
better and you can do that locally you
can do that for yourself you can do that
for your family you can do that for the
broader community and all of that's
worth it man it's worth making some
sacrifices for it's worth suffering for
to some degree and then you decompose
that into the day-to-day and
week-to-week strategies and actions that
you're undertaking the plans and the
activities that you're putting forward
to make that dream a reality to realize
it and then when the depression and
anxiety come along you think part of it
with depression it's like it's just
bloody endurance it's like you get up
and you work through the next hour you
try to stay on track you try to
implement your strategic plans to the
best of your ability and you hope and
you pray that you'll get through it you
know you'll get through it and that the
darkness will recede and you you you you
stay on track you eat even though you're
not hungry you get up even though you
want to stay in bed you interact with
people even though you'd rather be alone
and it's it's it's it's the benefit of
disciplined habits can can sustain you
it's like the boat you're rowing in
through a terrible storm leaks and all
and maybe you'll be overwhelmed but you
have the boat and you can roll forward
and that's what you've got and so
endurance is a huge part of it and then
I would say with its anxiety it's the
same thing it's like or very much the
same as you're terrified and and
uncertain but you move ahead to the best
of your ability and again you operate at
least to some degree on hope and if you
haven't got hope then you've got blind
bloody endurance and that's all
motivated by
some sense that you're working towards
something that's worthwhile working to
work you know and that is well that's
your own long-term well-being to treat
yourself properly
it's the stability and productivity and
harmony and health of your family that's
a huge deal and then it's whatever
benefit you can be to the community and
if you have to limp along and drag
yourself forward in order to maintain
that pathway then so be it
because it's better than the alternative
so and I'm not and I know that you can
become depressed enough so that you know
you're virtually immobilized but you do
what you can to fight it and you and
then you do what you can to treat it you
know it's like have you tried the
antidepressants have you gone to speak
to a professional have you done what you
need to do to investigate the causes of
your depression and anxiety because
often there's physical reasons that that
might be the case you know like I've
learned notoriously that a fair bit of
the negative emotion that I experienced
a seem to be associated with an
autoimmune problem that was associated
with food sensitivity Jesus like I
hadn't I I would have never believed
that was possible ten years ago even
though I didn't I had learned by that
point that my susceptibility the
negative emotion was definitely
exacerbated for example if I was hungry
so I knew there was some relationship
with food but I had no idea that it was
this profound as it turned out to be and
so but don't and then well the other
thing you can do too is that as the
negative emotion ramps up in intensity
the amount of time that you construe as
managable shrinks you know and if you're
extremely depressed and anxious then you
know you may be struggling to get
through the day and then you need a map
of what is going to constitute a
minimally acceptable day and that might
be one where you've done what you need
so that when you wake up
tomorrow things aren't worse right you
have to keep up with your obligations
and your duties at least enough so that
you're not degenerating downhill and you
the other thing too is that you you also
learned that you act out the things that
you would do when you're normal even
when you're depressed you know you don't
want to see people well it doesn't
matter you go see them cuz it's better
than not seeing them you know and you
find when you do see them that it's
better it'll go better than you think
but you can't isolate yourself and
you're anxious and so you want to avoid
you don't want to go out you'd rather
stay home and sit in the chair and just
sit there and like in a frozen positions
like you can't do that you have to go
out and go grocery shopping and go out
and have coffee and all of those things
it doesn't matter whether you enjoy them
it matters that you do them because
that's what you do that's what you do in
order to maintain your health and and so
a huge part of it is like head down
endurance and that'll get you through
bad times that endurance it's it's it's
such an under represented virtue that
ability to trudge forward under a trudge
forward unhappily under unfairly
burdensome load is a testament to
character if you can and then it's
something that should be encouraged and
valued so you know and I'm not making
the claim that people who are depressed
you can't get out of bed lack endurance
some do and some don't because
depression comes in very varied degrees
of intensity and and you can be laid out
completely by depression so I'm not
trying to make some arbitrary judgment
about who's got endurance and who hasn't
you can't do that from the outside but I
can say that endurance is one of the
tools you have to deal with chronic
discomfort and pain you know and even if
you have chronic pain it's interesting
because it's very much allied with
depression by the way all of the
research on chronic
back pain for example indicates and
chronic pain of all sorts is that the
more you allow your pain to render you
inactive the worse the outcome including
exacerbation of the pain a depression is
a pain disorder and so that's very much
worth thinking about - it's like move
forward move forward move forward you
know and if you need to talk to somebody
about what your plan is for the day or
the hour or the week then do that as
well and perhaps you also have to help
get the people around you to help a bit
I need a little bit of help getting up
in the morning I need to have breakfast
made for me so that all I knew when I
get up in my sin my terrible state of
fog and confusion and terrible anxiety
and depression is I have a shower
because that's what happens first and
then the next thing is I eat and then
that's better you're at least you're out
of bed and moving and that's that's a
start
you know so and then you endear and hope
and that's how it is and you do the same
thing when someone in your family is
sick or when you're facing a death all
of that it's like one bloody foot in
front of the other up the hill how are
you always so consistently composed and
confident oh yeah well I wouldn't say
that I am I know what you mean well look
you know I'm I'm not that young I'm just
about 60 years old and so I have a lot
of experience behind me and I've seen a
lot of things and I've learned to be
detached to some degree you know that's
one thing you learn as a clinician as
people are always talking to you about
terrible things and that difficulties in
their life and you can take that home
and and have it destroy you because
you're constantly exposed to the
troubles of existence and then there are
real troubles you know and I mean it's
not unique to clinicians you see that
with physicians and palliative care
workers and people who work in morgues
and emergency responders and like
there's lots of people who face
the the very difficult aspects of life
very frequently you detach yourself from
it to some degree you know and I don't
mean in a disinterested way I mean in a
in a way that is sort of allied with a
longer term view you know like if I'm
doing an interview now with with someone
who's attacking me and I can get
irritable I think I was too irritable in
the GQ interview for example which some
of you might have watched I think well
I'm not gonna jump to conclusions about
how this is going to go even even with
regards to how it feels right in the
moment we'll see how it unfolds across
time and I'll try to manage myself in
the moment with the least amount of
upset that I can manage and then it's
part of the doctrine of minimal minimal
necessary force like one of the things
I've learned if you're if you have a
dispute with someone and it needs to be
settled and maybe they need to change
more than you and that's not always the
case because sometimes the settling
requires change on your part but let's
say that they have to be defeated in
some sense in comparison to you you
don't want to defeat them any more than
necessary you know it's like you don't
knock your opponent to the ground and
then jump up and down on them three or
four times in triumph you know you you
you you pin them in linen and then let
them up minimal necessary force because
any more than that just produces a
counter reaction and so and I guess the
other thing is too is my motivation when
I'm engaged let's say in these
discussions is that I'm not trying to
win the argument I'm not trying to win
I'm trying to say what I think as
clearly as I can and there is there
might be an element there might be one
of the consequences of that might be
what appears to be a victory but the
victory is the victory for your ability
to articulate what you believe and
that's what I'm trying to do and so
that's another reason to stay composed
is like well okay this person has just
thrown a curveball at me it's like all
right so well I could be thinking well I
don't want to be undermined by that and
I don't want to make a fool of myself
and I don't want to be put on the spot
and of course all of those things are
true but mostly what I'm thinking about
is okay well now I've got that question
I want to answer as truthfully as I
possibly can
what do I think about what was just said
and I'm not calculating the outcome I'm
assuming this is a mark of faith right
this is the faith that the people have
talked about being something that has to
be manifested necessarily we'd be
talking about this since the dawn of
time
what's the faith the faith is that if
you say what you believe to be true then
whatever happens is the best thing that
could have happened and I believe that
so that's what I really believe it
partly because I believe that if you're
deceitful which is the opposite of that
or manipulative or malicious or
malevolent
but maybe primarily manipulative then
what you're acting out is your belief
that deceit will bring victory and I
just don't believe that at all I just I
think it's a preposterous claim and so
if Steve won't bring victory then truth
is what brings victory if there is such
a thing as truth and there's certainly
such a thing as deceit
so there must be such a thing as truth
and so and some of its just curiosity
too it's like well I'm going to say what
I think and see what happens
that's an adventure you know that's the
adventure of your life really and you
don't want to miss that because that's
what you've got in your life is for it
to be an adventure it's not an easy road
you know it's a stormy sea
and what you have is the adventure of
contending with God and the waves that's
what you have and the way you do that is
with truth and then that sort of takes
you out of that immediacy of the
conflict whoever it is that the conflict
with whoever it is that you're talking
to you're trying to align yourself with
something that's deeper and more
profound and more lasting but I'd like I
don't think that I am particularly
consistently composed and confident you
know I think I have faith in the truth
it's not the same thing and you know I'm
an emotional person obviously how do you
manage to read so much well a lot of
that's good fortune you know like I seem
to have a knack for reading it's not it
was a gift you know like when I was a
kid if I look at a word once I can
always spell it like I have it instantly
and I've been like that ever since I was
little and so I seem to have a facility
for very rapid verbal comprehension and
then my father taught me to read when I
was very young and I think it was the
combination of those two things that
enabled that for me you know I had the
natural proclivity a verbal ability you
know I my grudges supervisor very smart
guy Robert Peel guy I really like
he had trouble with spelling you know it
I don't know why sake that is people
have different talents and I had to tell
it for immediate recognition and memory
of words and and and I'm also very
verbally fluid here
so I think mostly it's an innate talent
you know now I also do know that the
more you read
generally speaking the faster you get my
wife is really like she always read but
she's really started to read more since
you go to Kendall she turns out to he
likes her Kindle she reads a lot more in
her reading speed has increased a lot a
lot of its practice you can try to speed
up your reading by reading a little
faster than you're comfortable with it I
don't know the research literature
indicating the utility of that but
practice is always useful the other
thing is is that you want to make it
part of habit you both conceptually and
practically a lot of people don't read
because they're afraid of books the
books aren't their friend so you might
want to get a few books and kind of make
them your friend you can start with
simpler books you know like fiction
there's lots of good fiction written
written for adolescents and children
it's pretty straightforward you can
start there if you're interested in
philosophy there's lots of simple guides
like the idiots guide to different
topics or a beginner's guide I read
those things all the time when I'm first
investigating a new topic you know I
start with the introductory material and
I make time for reading like and it was
that was encouraged in my family like
always read before I went to sleep I
read and I still do that somewhat less
so because I've become so distracted by
social media but you set aside a bit of
time every day to read it for me it was
always just before I went to bed I go to
bed turn the light read for oh when I
was a kid for hours but and if you do
something every day you do a lot of it
and so I would say well if you want to
read if you want to make yourself
educated is put aside 20 minutes a day
to read or ten you know some small
amount of time that you could actually
steal not two hours because good luck
it's very unlikely you'll manage that
but 20 minutes a day you know that's 2
hours a week that's 700 hours a year
you know that's even if you're a slow
reader that's a good number of books and
so you make it a habitual part of your
life and you decide that it's going to
be something that you value you
investigate carefully what resistances
you might have to that idea because you
might think well that's pseudo
intellectual or there's something more
productive I can be doing or I'm
intimidated by books or I hate books
because I wasn't good at reading when I
was a kid and I was humiliated because
of it or you know you've got something
against intellectuals or God there might
all sorts of resistances to picking up a
book then you can listen to audiobooks
that's a good way around that by hook or
by crook man
so you value it you make it a regular
part of your life you practice doing it
and and you you need a higher goal to
it's like well why should you read well
and so that you're more informed and you
can think better why should you be more
informed and think better because you
won't walk blindly into so many pits you
know you'll be able to negotiate better
in your life because you'll be more
informed and more verbally fluent and
you'll have a better sense of how the
world works and they'll hold your own in
conversations and that'll make you more
confident those are all unbelievably
good reasons to be highly literate is is
an incredibly massive massive advantage
practical advantage you know and it
shouldn't be underestimated so there are
drug-addicted mentally ill homeless
people in my city and it seems to keep
getting worse how do we help people who
don't want to be helped
well I think you do that by example
fundamentally there isn't any other way
I know of to help people who don't want
to be helped
and then I guess I think what you do is
you open up you it's the same thing I've
said many times is that you do what you
can to make the things around you better
you better your family better and then
whatever you can manage in your
community you know if you're interested
in the drug-addicted in the mentally ill
know there are volunteer you could
volunteer you could talk to those people
and listen because then you'd find out
what the hell their problems are and
then you'd have some sense about how
they might be helped you know but that's
a hard thing there's no helping from
above drug addiction and it's
combination of mental illness
unbelievably complicated problems
there's no simple solutions so and it
isn't even necessarily obvious that the
people that you see who are homeless and
drug-addicted and mentally ill don't
want to be helped is that sometimes they
have problems that are so absolutely
overwhelming that they can't be helped
in any real sense you know like if
they're unmedicated schizophrenic for
example with a drug problem
Scott it's just that's just a
nightmarish it's a nightmare of insane
complexity because schizophrenia is very
very difficult to deal with even even
with medication because the medication
that helps people who are schizophrenic
also tends to depress their positive
emotion and decrease their motivation
you know so
the medications are generally helpful
and the proper treatment guidelines if
you're schizophrenic generally are stay
with your medication because despite the
negative consequences of the medication
which aren't trivial the consequences of
not taking in our
and that's a real Hobson's choice right
it's a bit of Hell in both directions
but if you really want to know I would
say go have some contact with those
people and listen to them and learn what
the problems are maybe you could start
seeing what might be helpful it's a
really complicated problem and it's
different than the problem of helping
people who don't want to be helped
because you have to figure out who it is
that doesn't want to be helped first and
you don't want to assume that just
because someone's homeless that they
don't want to be helped I mean that
doesn't mean that it's easy to figure
out how to help them it's not easy it's
helping people is a very difficult
business and it's a very dangerous
business to because you get tangled up
in ways that you wouldn't expect and
that can be an occupational hazard let's
put it that way how do I stop ruminating
these thoughts are recurring and relate
to every and any embarrassing moment I
have ever had during my lifetime I'm a
76 year old woman well although here's
something you could try write down
everything that you're ruminating about
I know that seems counterproductive but
Laci ruminations come up accidentally
involuntarily unconsciously whereas if
you write down everything that you're
ruminating about you're facing them
voluntarily so I would say well open up
a journal or word document whatever and
write down every time you ruminate about
something write it down and write down
every rumination you can remember
exhaustively write them all down that
would be the first thing and the second
thing is standard behavioral therapy
practice the second thing the next thing
would be write down why you think they
happened so that you get a good causal
account and then write down well what
you might have done about them then but
more importantly what you could do about
them in the future to avoid them because
it doesn't matter that something
embarrassing happened to you
what matters is whether or not you're
likely to repeat it in the future but my
suspicions are that even if you just you
could just start simply write down every
ruminating ruminating thought that you
have voluntarily and think about them in
detail and write them down in detail get
every little word down and then you have
that document and then when you have a
thought and start to ruminate on it then
sit down later after the ruminating
thought goes away and bring it to mind
voluntarily so every time you ever
thought you don't want to have later
practice having that thought on purpose
and try that for about a month and see
what happens because it's often the case
that if you start thinking about the
thoughts you're ruminating on
consciously and confront them
voluntarily that they will start to go
away so you could try that you could try
that that that should help
what's the best method to retain what
you read and to be able to use it in
conversation oh well
it's very difficult ready to retain
anything without recalling it so look if
you encounter something and then you
encounter it again you can usually
recognize that you've encountered it
before
that's recognition memory so it's it's
an important form of memory it's it's
it's the memory that's associated with
familiarity but it's not the same as
being able to use something exactly it's
a rather shallow form of memory even
though it's necessary in order to be
able to use something you have to recall
it this is also very useful hint for
studying like if you're studying and you
have to remember what you want to do is
study and then you want to write down
what you just learned so you read a
paragraph you close the book and you
write down what you remember or you read
a chapter and you close the book and you
write down what you remember or at least
you sit there and you try to remember
because the way you remember is by
practicing remembering okay so if you're
reading and you want to use it in
conversation then you have to think
about what you read you have to put it
in your own words it's also often
helpful to close the book and write it
down or to associate it with some
problem that you're currently trying to
solve you have to take the knowledge and
make it your own and then and then that
alters the structure through which you
look at the world and that changes the
way that you think so that when you have
a conversation the next time that you're
going to have the conversation in a
different way so merely reading isn't
enough you have you have to read and
think and recall and it's the act of
recalling that produces the remembering
and it's that act of remembering that
puts that material at hand for you so
okay well look I'm just about done here
it's 11:35 so I've gone for 19 minutes
and I hear people rattling around
upstairs and I have to fly to Zurich
today and so I'm going to stop out I'm
going to stop here so I'll find
one more question and answer it and then
I just found out I'm having a girl
congratulations what can I do to raise
her to think for herself and not fall
into the modes of thinking proposed by
popular culture well you can let her
think for herself when she's a kid
you know what you do is so that she
practices doing that you know and so
that means to consciously encourage as
much autonomy as possible so how do you
do that well let's say she's a little
kid she's three and she started to get
interested in clothing so you late
clothing out of the bed and you say what
you can wear this or you can wear this
you let her make autonomous decisions
you know with kids you don't want to let
them choose from an infinite menu you
want to give them a constraint menu but
what you want to do with your daughter
is allow her to make as many decisions
as she can possibly make as early as
possible you know and that doesn't mean
the children always know what's best for
themselves or any nonsense like that it
just means that you're going to
encourage her autonomy to every in every
measure that you can manage and that
means you're gonna have to be brave and
allow her to subject herself to a
certain number of risks so you you you
raise her to think for herself by
letting her think for herself and and
that can start that can start quite
early um I would say when she's a
teenager she's going to fall into the
modes of thinking proposed by popular
culture because that's part of being
enculturated and socialized it's
virtually inevitable and it's even
somewhat desirable but what you hope is
that you've you've encouraged the
capacity for autonomous thinking to a
sufficient degree that it's likely to
integrate with that more intense teenage
socialization and then reemerge so you
get someone who
the other side as an autonomous
individual and that works with boys and
girls so so you know let's I guess you
do what Geppetto did and Pinocchio is
the first thing you decide is well you
don't want to raise a puppet you know
you want to raise an autonomous person
and and then you think through what what
does it mean to be an autonomous person
what sort of person do you want your job
to be what what sort of person do you
want to encourage your child to be and
then having having having established
that vision in mind that's going to
guide your choices but at least you're
making the right choices you don't want
someone who's dependent and whiny and
cringy and and and more frightened than
they need to be and martyred martyr like
and vengeful and malicious and
manipulative and mendacious all of those
things you want someone who can make
their own judgments you can ask kids
what they think pretty damn early like
you have to be careful and not push them
beyond their capacity but if you know
your child you'll be able to see what
level of decision-making they're capable
of engaging it and then you would
encourage them to mature as rapidly as
they can you know and that also means
that you have to not allow yourself to
fall too in love with the dependent and
needy creature that your infant will be
to fulfill your own emotional needs you
want to detach and and encourage to
mature as rapidly and as comprehensively
as possible and that will work you know
and some of that some of that is
negotiation with your child you find out
what they think what do you think about
this what do you think about who should
do the work in the house how should we
split it up like they can be engaged in
the decision-making process is a very
early age and and part of that that
encouragement is going to be reflected
in your implicit attitude that the child
is a real person who's capable of
imposing their will yes in a realistic
sense in the world on the world and
doing that in a competent and excuse me
competent and confident manner so but at
least the beginning is the desire to do
that you want to raise them confident
autonomous courageous truthful person
and then you reward them when they're
like that and you notice it and you tell
them good work you did that right keep
it up
that's the right thing and you tell them
why what they did was right you know in
a detailed way and that that's very
powerful you wait and you lurk and you
wait for something that you want to have
happen and you say yes well we'd like to
see a lot more of that good work you do
that with yourself and with your partner
too it's very powerful technique alright
everyone I'm going to say goodbye
hopefully I'll do another one of these
in February although I'm not certain
maybe at the end of January I have a
couple of days there but I'm going to
Australia in February and that's going
to be very busy so but maybe I can do I
like doing this maybe I can do another
one in January near the end so just one
last thing I just want to let everybody
know remind everybody that I am leaving
patreon on the 15th of January and so
thanks for your support over the last
couple of years and hopefully hopefully
my next book will be better than the
last one was that's the plan that's why
I'm doing my best to manage that and and
hopefully we'll all have a good year you
know and aim high and all of that so
good see you and we'll talk in something
approximating a month bye